<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jeremy Mathevet</title>
    <link>http://blog.mathevet.xyz/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jeremy Mathevet</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 May 2015 19:49:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.mathevet.xyz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>SOCKS proxy via an SSH tunnel</title>
      <link>http://blog.mathevet.xyz/socks-proxy-via-an-ssh-tunnel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2015 19:49:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.mathevet.xyz/socks-proxy-via-an-ssh-tunnel/</guid>
      <description>You are behind a restrictive firewall and you aspire to more freedom? You need to access an Intranet website located in a different environment than yours? You are far from your home country, and can&amp;rsquo;t live one minute more without your favourite TV shows, that you can&amp;rsquo;t watch because of the localisation restrictions?
You can communicate via port 22? Do you have an SSH server that could access the content you want?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSH: RSA/DSA authentication</title>
      <link>http://blog.mathevet.xyz/ssh-rsadsa-authentication/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 12:53:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.mathevet.xyz/ssh-rsadsa-authentication/</guid>
      <description>Password authentication is good but can be dangerous, because it is weak against brute force attacks. There are some mechanisms which allow to mitigate this treat. There are also safer authentication mechanisms for SSH, like public key auhtentication.
We&amp;rsquo;re going to create a key pair from our client, a public and a private. We send the public key to the server. Thus, when the client tries to connect, the server communicates by encrypting communications with the public key.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dive into Git</title>
      <link>http://blog.mathevet.xyz/dive-into-git-en/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2011 17:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.mathevet.xyz/dive-into-git-en/</guid>
      <description>Git is a decentralized system control system (VCS) created by Linus Torvalds. This is a very powerful and popular tool. It is used for the Linux kernel development (and many other famous projects). It is so appreciated that the kernel developers are now wondering how they survived without it when it did not exist.
With so much praise, I wanted to test this tool. It&amp;rsquo;s not difficult to tame, however, the way it works is a bit different than other VCS (especially SVN, that I had already used), mainly because of the decentralization that characterizes Git.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>